Okay, we are taking up today on דף כ"א *Daf Kaph Aleph*
21 and we are up to אמר רב פפא Rav Pappa *Amar
Rav
Papa*, it is 10 lines from the top, or 12 lines from
the top, beginning of the line, אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa*.
So we had two opinions about which prohibition you transgress
when you do these types of שבועות shavuos, *Shavuot*, right? When you
make a נדר neder? *Nedar*, a vow which changes the status of
an object, the prohibition is לא lo. יחל דברו *Lo Yachel Devaro*,
that's pretty accepted. There there's an idea that you have created, I
assume that yesterday there was a focus on or there was a
discussion about the fundamental difference between a נדר neder, *Nedar* and a
שבועה Shvua *Shvua*, where a נדר neder, *Nedar* changes the status of
the object, whereas a שבועה shvuah *Shvua* relates to the person, you're
saying about what you will or won't do. So when you take
a vow and you change the status of the object, the Torah
says לא lo, יחל דברו *Lo Yachel Devaro*, you cannot allow the
words to be negated, but it is not about swearing falsely, it
is about doing some act that negates those words, that disregards the
status that you've created in the object. That's what a נדר neder?
*Nedar* is. But the question is, what are the different prohibitions for
a שבועה shvuah *Shvua*? So if you take an oath about something
that is purposeless, like you make an oath about something that is
obvious or something that is obviously true or obviously false, that's called
a שבועת שוא Shvuas Shav, *Shvuat Shav* and you transgress לא תשא
את שם ה' אלקיך לשוא Lashav *Lo Tisa Et Shem Hashem Elokecha
Lashav*. It's a purposeless oath. But the thing that has not been
explained in the משניות *Mishnayot* is, what about the classic שבועות shvuas,
*Shvuas* we're talking about? Either you take a false oath about events
in the past, אכלתי ולא אכלתי achalti velo achalti *Achalti Velachalti*, or
you take an oath to do something in the future and you
don't do it. So the first opinion said that a past oath
is a שבועת שוא Shvuas Shav. *Shvuat Shav*, which is a little
strange, but seems to be the point that there's no impact of
your words. I mean you've lied, but it's not like the שבועה
shvuah. *Shvua* had some sort of bindingness to it, so that's considered
just meaningless. A שבועה shvuah *Shvua* about the future that you don't
keep is לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר *Lo Tishavu Bishmi Lashaker*, that you've
taken an oath and then you have made it false, you've falsified
your words. That's the first opinion. The second opinion, which we're looking
at now, is saying what I think is more intuitive to us,
that using an oath to lie about the past is a שבועת
שקר Shvuas Sheker, *Shvuat Sheker*. That if you say you did something
and you didn't do it, you're lying, that's a שבועת שקר Shvuas
Sheker. *Shvuat Sheker*. Taking an oath about the future, he says that
is the same as a נדר neder *Nedar*, לא יחל דברו *Lo
Yachel Devaro*. And the logic is that that, like a נדר neder
*Nedar*, creates a status in the object, and then you cannot disregard
that status that your vow has had effect. When you take an
oath to do something or not to do something, that creates an
obligation and then you cannot violate that obligation. That's the לא יחל
דברו *Lo Yachel Devaro*. I should mention that against both of these
positions, the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says probably the easiest idea. The רמב"ם
Rambam *Rambam* says that whether it's about the past or about the
future, it's called a שבועת שקר Shvuas Sheker *Shvuat Sheker*. If you're
lying about the past or you take a vow to do something
in the future and you don't keep it, you have made a
שבועת שקר Shvuas Sheker *Shvuat Sheker*. But that is not what we're
saying now, we're saying that according to this opinion in the future
is לא יחל דברו *Lo Yachel Devaro*. So let's take a look
at what?
The question was raised yesterday. You know that you can do התרת
נדרים nidarim *Hatarat Nedarim*, but the same way you do התרת נדרים
*Hatarat Nedarim* you do התרת שבועות shvuos *Hatarat Shvuot*, right?
If it's future-oriented, yeah.
Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay.
אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa*, הדרי ביה אבהו לאו lav בפירוש
איתמר *hadre bi Abahu lav beferush itmar*, that statement that I just
told you, that the past is שקר sheker, *Sheker* and the future
is לא יחל *Lo Yachel*, was a statement of רבי אבהו Rabbi
Avahu *Rabbi Abahu* in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. He
did not say that position explicitly, אלא מכללא איתמר *ela mikhlala itmar*,
it was inferred from some other statement he said. דאמר רבי אידי
בר אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר רב יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן *De'amar
Rabbi Idi bar Abin amar Rav Amram amar Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi
Yochanan*, so you have a whole sort of tradition here that said
in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. רבי יהודה אומר משום
רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Yose HaGlili*, and that
statement in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said that רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* said in the name of רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi
Yose HaGlili*, so a lot of people being quoted. כל לא תעשה
lo taaseh שבתורה לאו lav. שיש בו מעשה לוקין עליו *Kol lo
ta'aseh shebaTorah, lav sheyesh bo ma'aseh lokin alav*, any prohibition in the
Torah if it has an action you get lashes. ושאין בו מעשה
אין לוקין עליו *Veshein bo ma'aseh ein lokin alav*, and if it
has no action, it's passive, you do not get lashes. חוץ *chutz*,
the exception is, מנשבע *minishba*, taking an oath, ומימר *umemar*, doing תמורה
*temurah*, transferring the status of trying to transfer the status of one
קרבן korban *korban* to another animal, transfer the קדושה *kedusha*, ומקלל חבירו
בשם *umekalel chavero bashem*, and cursing somebody with the name of God.
Now all of those you'll notice are speech acts, so it doesn't
really mean literally there's no act whatsoever, but normally we don't call
a speech act an act. It's just speech, it's not a physical
act. So therefore he says these are the only times where you
get lashes even though there is no act but we get lashes
for these acts of speech. But there are other acts of speech
you do not get lashes for. Okay, so that's those are the
exceptions.
So נשבע מנלן and now we're not going to look at the
other two, we're going to look only at the one that's interesting
to us. Where do I know about taking an oath? So אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai, so Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai, אמר קרא, Amar kra, the pasuk says, לא תשא
שם ה' אלהיך לשוא, Lo tisa shem Hashem Elokecha lashav, do not
take God's name in vain, כי לא ינקה, Ki lo yenakeh, because
God will not
forgive, forgive or cleanse if you take His name in vain. בית
דין של מעלה אין מנקין אותו, Beis din shel maalah ein menakin
oso, so the heavenly court will not cleanse you, אבל בית דין
של מטה מלקין אותו ומנקין אותו, Aval beis din shel mata malkin
oso umenakin oso, but the lower court, they will cleanse you, they'll
give you lashes and they will cleanse you. So it's funny, we
tend to think of מלקות Malkos as a punishment, but if you
remember from מכות, Makos,
right, there's all these cases where you get כרת Kares and we
understand that if the court gives you lashes, you are exempt from
כרת. Kares. So here too, actually, we make a דרשה Derasha to
understand—I mean that's pretty heavy, God will never forgive you if you
take His name in vain, and we make a דרשה Derasha to
say no, if we do something to you, we give you lashes,
that actually will be a way in which you will be forgiven.
So they don't reverse the import of the verse.
Well what can I tell you? Okay, now that is debated, but
that's what's understood. So that's the source that you get lashes for
a שבועת שוא, Shvuas Shav okay, that when you take an oath
that is totally in vain, something that is either totally true, totally
false, or to no purpose, okay, that is a שבועת שוא. Shvuas
Shav
So that's the example of a שבועה shvuah where you do get
lashes. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Papa le-Abaye, so
Rav Papa said to Abaye, you know because ודילמא
הכי קאמר רחמנא, Udilma hachi ka'amar Rachmana, how do you learn the
pasuk that way? Maybe the pasuk says לא ינקה כלל, Lo yenakeh
klal,
that you're never going to be cleansed if you take God's name
in vain in an oath. So he said back to him, אי
כתיב כי לא ינקה, Ei kesiv ki lo yenakeh, this pasuk, a
person will never be cleansed, כדקאמרת, Kedeka'amart, it would be like you
said. השתא דכתיב כי לא ינקה ה', Hashta dikesiv ki lo yenakeh
Hashem, God won't cleanse you, השם הוא דאינו מנקה, Hashem hu de'eino
menakeh, God won't cleanse you, אבל בית דין של מטה מלקין אותו
ומנקין אותו. Aval beis din shel mata malkin oso umenakin oso. Okay,
so that's where you know that a שבועת שוא shvuas shav. does
get מלקות. Malkos. So the discussion however went on. אשכחן שבועת שוא,
Ashkechan Shvuas Shav, we found an oath for naught. שבועת שקר מנלן,
Shvuas Sheker minalan, how do you know about if a person takes
an oath that is a lie, a שבועת שקר, Shvuas Sheker, a
false oath? רבי יוחנן דידיה אמר, Rabbi Yochanan didei amar, so Rabbi
Yochanan here said in his own name, not in the name of
like of Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai like he did before, לשוא לשוא
שתי פעמים. Lashav lashav shtei pe'amim.
It says לשוא Lashav twice in the pasuk. It says לא תשא
שם ה' אלהיך לשוא, Lo tisa shem Hashem Elokecha lashav, right, and
then כי לא ינקה ה' את אשר ישא את שמו לשוא. Ki
lo yenakeh Hashem es asher yisa es shemo lashav.
So it says לשוא Lashav twice. Why is it saying it twice?
So לשוא לשוא שתי פעמים, Lashav lashav shtei pe'amim, אם אינו עניין
לשבועת שוא, Im eino inyan lishvuas shav, it doesn't have to tell
you that it's referring to a שבועת שוא shvuas shav. because one
time saying לשוא lashav? would have done that, תניהו עניין לשבועת שקר.
Taneihu inyan lishvuas sheker.
It comes to tell you—right, exactly, it's sort of like אין ריבוי
אחר ריבוי אלא לרבות, Ein ribui achar ribui ela lerabos, it's an
extra thing and we don't need it to say that שוא, Shav,
you just said that, so it's come to expand it and say
even a שבועת שקר. Shvuas Sheker Okay, so you see that even
a שבועת שקר shvuas sheker you get lashes. Now we're not done,
because we want to know what is the case of a שבועת
שקר shvuas sheker that you get lashes? Not so obvious that you
do, or not so obvious you needed the pasuk to tell me
that. Let's take a look. והוה בה רבי אבהו, Vehavah bah Rabbi
Abahu,
and Rabbi Abahu asked the following question after this discussion: הי שבועת
שקר היכי דמי, Hi Shvuas Sheker heichi dami,
when you need to tell me you get lashes, מלקות, Malkos, for
a שבועת שקר, shvuas sheker what case of שבועת שקר shvuas sheker.
are we talking about? אילימא שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל, Ilima shvua shelo
ochel ve'achal, if it's an oath that you won't eat and then
you went ahead and actively ate, לאו שיש בו מעשה הוא, Lav
sheyesh bo maaseh hu, that's
we said we're trying to teach you that you get lashes when
you didn't do an action. So that case you did an action,
you ate. אלא דאמר שבועה אוכל ולא אכל, Ela de'amar shvua ochel
velo achal,
okay, so it'll be the opposite case. He took an oath that
he would eat and then he passively did not eat. So that
would be not an action. But the problem is you don't get
lashes then. והאי מי לוקה? Vehai mi lokeh?
Who says you get lashes in that case? והאיתמר, Veha'itmar, but it's
taught: שבועה אוכל כיכר זו היום, Shvua ochel kikar zu hayom, if
somebody takes an oath that I will eat this loaf of bread
today, ועבר היום ולא אכלה, Ve'avar hayom velo achlah,
and the day passed and he didn't eat it, רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש דאמרו תרווייהו, Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish de'amru taveihu, it's a debate
of Rabbi Yochanan—sorry, Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish, they both say אינו
לוקה, Eino lokeh, you do not get lashes in that case. Now
for different reasons they say this. רבי יוחנן אמר אינו לוקה משום
דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה, Rabbi Yochanan amar eino lokeh mishum dehvei
lav she'ein bo maaseh, because it's a prohibition because it was transgressed
without an action, וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו, Vechol
lav she'ein bo maaseh ein lokin alav, and anything without an action
you don't get lashes. וריש לקיש אמר, Ve-Resh Lakish amar, he gives
a different reason: אינו לוקה, Eino lokeh, yeah this we've had like
three times now, אינו לוקה Eino lokeh משום דהוי התראת ספק, mishum
dehvei hasras safek,
because it is a doubtful warning and again it's—
That's warning meaning that if you tell the person better eat it,
if you don't eat it, you're going to get lashes, and he
says anyway, so he you don't know if he's going to transgress
or not transgress. You'll only know at the end of the day.
So Rashi says, and this is always important by התראת ספק, hatra'as
safek, is that often התראת ספק hatra'as safek is based on the
idea that the התראה hatra'ah has to be immediately before the transgression.
So here, if the right before he does some, right before he
doesn't do something, you don't know if he's going to do it
or not. Now, you could say you gave him the warning at
the last second of the day, okay,
but in a normal case it would not be a definite warning.
So let me just finish this and then you can ask your
question. התראת ספק התראת ספק לא שמה התראה. hatra'as safek hatra'as safek
lo shemah hatra'ah. So therefore it can't be about an oath that
I will eat and then you passively don't eat because
actually it can be future and you do eat, you transgress because
then you get מלקות, malkus, but then you don't need the פסוק.
pasuk. It can't be something you'll do and then you passively don't
do because actually you don't get מלקות malkus in that case. So
היכי דמי, heichay damay, so what is the only case of שבועת
שקר shvuas sheker that we could be telling need to tell me
you get lashes and that you do get lashes? So the גמרא
Gemara says, or I guess I lost my place, hold on, לא
שמה דאמר רבי אבהו, lo shemah d'amar Rabbi Avahu, so רבי אבהו
Rabi Abahu says, תהא באכלתי ולא אכלתי. tehei be'achalti velo achalti.
So it's telling you you get lashes for the other case of
שקר, sheker when you take an oath about the past and you're
lying. You say you've eaten and you haven't, you say you haven't
and you have. That is the case. That's the case where you
actually do get מלקות. malkus. ומה ישנא, umai shna, what makes that
type of a שבועה shvuah more getting lashes than if it's future
oriented? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, בפירוש ריבתה תורה, befirush ribsa Torah,
שבועת שקר דומה לשוא. shvuas sheker domeh leshav. That the תורה Torah
said לשוא לשוא, lashav lashav, so it meant something like a שבועת
שוא. shvuas shav A שקר sheker that was like a שבועת שוא.
shvuas shav. מה שוא לשעבר אף שקר נמי לשעבר. mah shav l'she'avar
af sheker nami l'she'avar.
So the same way שבועת שוא shvuas shav is about the past,
like you say something that is about or the present that's obviously
true, it's a purposeless or something obviously false.
So I want to say one or two points clarifying this and
then Bobby has a question. Point number one is first of all
you'll notice in this statement it considers both a future and a
past oriented. It says what type of שבועת שקר shvuas sheker. are
we talking about? Are we talking about the future? Then you don't
always get מלקות malkus for that. So we must be talking about
the past. So this is presumably where רמב"ם gets his position
that whether it's future or past it's שבועת שקר shvuat sheker because
here it's being called שקר sheker in both directions, although before we've
never had that position. Number two, what is the emphasis of saying
that the past is you get מלקות malkus and that's similar to
לשוא? What conceptually is the difference between אכלתי ולא אכלתי achalti velo
achalti, and the future? And the difference is whether the basic transgression
is the act of the שבועה shvuah. or the basic transgression is
what you do later. Right? When I say falsely, swear falsely אכלתי
achalti or לא אכלתי, lo achalti, I am lying through שבועה. shavuah.
So I am or if I so I'm essentially using God's name
to deceive and to pervert and so on. That's a שבועת שקר.
sheker. If I say something obvious, patently
true, the sky is blue—well, it's not a cloudy day—the sky, whatever
it is, there is a sky, right, or gold is gold or
something patently false, wood is gold or whatever it is, then at
that moment my speech act is using God's name in vain in
an oath. Okay, so that's the similarity. That's called a שבועת שוא
שבועת שקר shvuas shav shvuas sheker where he gets מלקות malkus for
the very speech act of taking a שבועה shavuah that way. If
I say I will do something or I won't and then I
don't keep to it, even according to the רמב"ם you transgress because
of שקר because by not keeping to it I made it false.
Part of the whole problem was not the moment I took the
oath, part of the problem was whether I kept to what I
said in the future. And therefore, as if I actively violated it
I'll also get מלקות, malkus, but if I just passively I won't.
But it's also why conceptually it's a different type of a problem
than when the actual problem is in the שבועה shavuah itself and
that is the position we're saying now. Bobby, you have a question?
No, I think it's more complicated than I realized. I thought originally
to ask you whether the word will is so powerful. If you
say I will eat a loaf of bread, does that become an
oath?
No, no, you need to specifically use technical terms to refer to
an oath. First of all, there's a question that a שבועה shavuah,
has to be בשם השם beshem Hashem and all these examples are
not בשם השם. beshem Hashem. So often we assume that if you
used one of the technical words you're alluding to the fact that
it's in God's name even though you don't say it. But it's
specifically when you use a technical word
like
שבועה. shavuah But it's
normally a promise, you know, there's a גמרא Gemara that makes a
דרשה drasha that how do you know you're supposed to keep your
word because it makes a דרשה drasha on the פסוק pasuk of
הין צדק יהיה לכם. hin tzedek yihiyeh lachem. You should have a
righteous הין, hin, which is a measure, like a quart, but the
word הין hin also in Aramaic means yes. So the גמרא gemara
says your הין, hin, your yes should be righteous, your no should
be righteous, you're supposed to keep your word, but that's more, you
know, an ethical teaching and it's not this. This is when you
use a technical word to mean שבועה. shavuah Yeah.
So in the case
that you just explained where you don't get מלקות, malkos, what is
your status?
You've transgressed a לאו passively. So, you know, there's like other ways
in which you transgress a לאו.
And when does a קרבן korban, come in?
Oh, so the קרבן, korban so this was also unusual because normally
you only bring a קרבן korban when it's חייב כרת. chayav kareis.
This on the one hand is not חייב כרת, chayav kareis, on
the other hand it's לא ינקה השם, lo yenakeh Hashem, so it's
pretty weighty from that perspective. The קרבן korban is only when you
transgress unintentionally. Okay? So a קרבן korban is only for a either
future-oriented, everybody agrees, I will eat, I won't eat, past is the
debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב chayav for an oath in the
past, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael does not. And you are unintentional. So
if it's future, you say you'll eat and you forget about your
שבועה shavuah and you don't, okay? Or you say you won't and
you forget. It has to be, it has to be unintentional.
Past has to be that you swore that you did something but
you forgot, you really didn't, but you were mistaken. Okay?
But you didn't purpose, you're not bringing
a קרבן korban because if you did it on... so if you
take one of those שבועות, shvuot not a שוא, shav, not like
something obviously true or false, okay? But something about what you will
do or according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva what you have done
or haven't done, if you do it unintentionally, you make it false
or you said falsely, you bring a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh
veyored. If you intentionally violate, so if it's past-oriented you get מלקות,
malkos, if it's future-oriented only if you do an action. Okay? So
if it's future-oriented and you do no action, then it's like any
other prohibition that you transgress without an action and you know, God
will take care of it
but there's no extra accountability?
Exactly. In a way it's harder because לא ינקה השם, lo yenakeh
Hashem, so you're really in trouble. Okay, yes, Mrs. Does it have
to be done before
witnesses or a בית דין? beis din?
Oh, to get מלקות? malkos? To get מלקות, malkos, yes. So it
has to be like two people
are arguing and one says I swear I'm never speaking to you.
Right,
right. It's got to be a formal...
no, no, no, to be a שבועה shavuah, it does not have
to be formal, it does not have to be in בית דין,
beis din, it could be just a person in his home by
himself or herself takes that שבועה, shavuah... but you're not going to
give a guy מלקות malkos unless there's evidence to the fact. But
for example the קרבן korban. issue, the same way if I at
my home ate חלב cheilev and nobody knows but I know and
I did it unintentionally, I would bring a קרבן. korban. If I
took a שבועה shavuah, and didn't live up to it and I
know, I bring a קרבן. korban, But for מלקות malkos you need
evidence. And that's true, you do not need it in the presence
of witnesses or בית דין beis din for it to be binding.
When we talk about a שבועה shavuah later about a שבועה shvuah
in a בית דין beis din context, we'll talk about בית דין
beis din a little bit more, but here you do not need
that.
Okay, thank you. Okay fine. Okay good. So let's continue now. Okay,
so this is the question about the chart as well. Yeah, this
is the question right, I know. Okay, this is the question about
what prohibition you transgress
and but the פשט pshat is, and this is what we're going
to focus on now, that for a past-oriented שבועה, shvua. because the
violation is with the word immediately with the word, you get מלקות
malkos even though there's no action. With a future-oriented שבועה... shvua Can
you say that again, I'm sorry? Past-oriented שבועה, shvua, I ate, I
didn't eat, so like a שוא shav since the violation is with
the act of the שבועה shvua immediately, then you get מלקות, malkos,
then you do get מלקות, malkos, okay, even though there's no action.
Future-oriented is only if then you actively transgress it. So we're going
to focus on this idea that you get מלקות malkos for a
שבועת שקר in the past. Let's take a look. Okay.
איתיביה רבי ירמיה לרבי אבהו. Esvei Rabi Yirmiyah leRabi Abahu. רבי ירמיה
Rabi Yirmiyah asked on רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu, about this point of
the מלקות malkos point. שבועה שלא אוכל ככר זו. Shvuah shelo ochal
kikar zu. Somebody takes an oath that I won't eat this loaf
of bread, and then he repeats the oath. שבועה שלא אוכלנה. Shvuah
shelo ochlena. I won't eat it. שבועה שלא אוכלנה. Shvuah shelo ochlena.
I take... I won't eat it. So you have three שבועות, shvuot?
okay? ואכלה. Veachala. And he ate it. אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino
chayav ela achas. So he only brings one because אין שבועה חלה
על שבועה. ein shvuah chala al shvuah. If you already are bound
by an oath to do something, another oath is not... is not
meaningful and you do not get separate lashes for that.
Unless he adds to it, right?
I won't eat it today... Right, there's questions about if you're מוסיף
mosif etc., we'll deal with all that later. Okay. אין
שבועה חלה על שבועה.
Ein shvuah
chala al shvuah. Oh,
no, that's right. אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino chayav ela achas. זו
היא. Zo hi. And this is a משנה mishnah later, and the
משנה mishnah says, זו היא שבועת ביטוי שחייבין על זדונה מלקות ועל
שגגתה קרבן. zo hi shvuas bituy shechayavin al zedonah malkos veal shegagasah
korban. This is the שבועה shvua of enunciation that you, if you
willfully transgress, you get מלקות, malkos, lashes, and if you unintentionally transgress,
you bring a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban olah veyored. Okay, so this,
it says this is the one and it's future-oriented,
so it seems like it's coming to exclude the case of a
past-oriented שבועה. shvua, זו היא, zo hi, this is the case where
you get מלקות. malkos. לאתויי מאי? le'atuye mai? What is that excluding?
לאו לאתויי אכלתי ולא אכלתי? lav le'atuye achalti velo achalti? Isn't it
implicitly excluding the case of if you took an oath that I
about the past that I did eat or haven't eaten, דלא לקי,
delo laky, that you would not get lashes in that case? So
how can you say you get lashes about a שבועה shvua in
the past? So פשיטא? pshita? He says that, no, no, that's not
what it's excluding. לאתויי, le'atuye, it's excluding אכלתי ולא אכלתי, achalti velo
achalti, it is excluding the case of past, but not from lashes,
but מקרבן, mikorban, from bringing a קרבן, korban. because it said two
things: the future one, you get lashes and a קרבן. korban. So
a past one, you get what? So he so yes, you still
get lashes, says רבי אבהו, but you don't get the קרבן. korban
And that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. זו היא דשגגתה קרבן עולה ויורד, zo hi deshegagasah korban
olah veyored,
this is the one in the future when if you do it
unintentionally, you bring a קרבן korban of עולה ויורד olah veyored of
changing
value, אבל אכלתי ולא אכלתי, aval achalti velo achalti, a past שבועה,
shvua לא. And who is that? רבי ישמעאל היא דאמר אינו חייב
אלא על העתיד לבוא. Rabbi Yishmael hi deamar eino chayav ela al
haasid lavo. That's רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, right? That is the whole
two which are four, the two that are explicit in the תורה
Torah that you bring a קרבן korban, is a שבועה shvua for
the future. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says there are two more about
the past, but רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael disagrees with that. So when
this משנה mishnah says a future שבועה shvua is when you get
lashes and a קרבן, korban. that's the one. So says that's excluding
a past according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So according to רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, a past שבועה, shvua you do not bring a
קרבן.
korban Just a regular לא תעשה that you've transgressed because you did
it
בשוגג.
beshogeg. Right, exactly. Okay, אבל מלקי לקי, aval milka laky, you would
still get lashes. All right, so now we look, we turn the
דף כ"א עמוד ב'. daf chaf aleph amud beis. אימא סיפא, eima
seifa, let's look, however, at the end of the משנה. mishnah. The
end of the משנה mishnah gives an example of a שבועת שוא.
shvuas shav, Again, a שבועת שוא shvuas shav is something patently true
or patently false. Okay, and it says after it describes a שבועת
שוא, shvuas shav it ends by saying the following: זו היא שבועת
שוא, zo hi shvuas shav, this is a like a, you know,
a שבועה shvua in vain, שחייבין על זדונה מלקות, shechayavin al zedonah
malkos, that we've already said that a שבועת שוא shvuas shav you
get lashes for if it's willful, ועל שגגתה פטור, veal shegagasah patur,
but if it's unintentional, you're exempt because it is not a שבועת
ביטוי. shvuas bituy. Okay, a שבועה shvua in vain has no קרבן
korban. associated with it. All right, so the גמרא gemara. says again,
what is that excluding? So again, a שבועת שוא shvuas shav, is,
we're calling it like past-oriented, meaning it doesn't create an obligation for
you to act or not act in a certain way. So we
say the שבועת שוא shvuas shav, is when you, you get מלקות
malkos and don't bring a קרבן. korban, So what's it contrasted to?
זו היא לאתויי מאי? zo hi le'atuye mai? In contrast to what?
So notice in, here's the point, I think, to help us focus.
The משנה mishnah gave two cases. It says a שבועת שוא, shvuas
shav you get lashes and no קרבן, korban meaning lashes intentional, no
קרבן korban if unintentional. A שבועה shvua about the future, if you
and then you don't do what you said you would do, it's
either going to be, it'll be unintentional, it'll be lashes if intentional,
קרבן korban. if unintentional. Okay, and both of them said, "these are."
So we talked about a שבועת שוא, shvuas shav, we've talked about
a שבועה shvua about the future. The only case we're not talking
about is about אכלתי ולא אכלתי, achalti velo achalti, right? So that
seems to be always the implicit one being rejected. So the first
time we said, okay, what's implicitly rejected is if it's past, אכלתי
ולא אכלתי, achalti velo achalti. no קרבן. korban, But now we're saying,
well, what's the שבועת שוא shvuat shav case excluding? The only other
case to exclude is אכלתי ולא אכלתי. achalti velo achalti, So let's
take a look at the גמרא. gemara זו היא לאתויי מאי? zo
hi le'atuye mai? What is it excluding? מאי לאו לאתויי אכלתי ולא
אכלתי? mai lav le'atuye achalti velo achalti? That's the only case not
mentioned in the משנה. mishnah. And what's it saying? For a שבועת
שוא, shvuat shav, you get מלקות, malkos, but presumably, and no קרבן,
korban but presumably for אכלתי ולא אכלתי, achalti velo achalti. you don't
even get מלקות. malkos. So presumably it's saying דלא לקי, delo laky,
that you don't get מלקות. malkos.
That would seem like the most serious violation of all of
a שבועת שקר.
Of all the שבועות shvuot you could take, that's the worst one
because you're using the שבועה shvua basically to lie and to get
away with something and to deceive.
Right, it could be בית דין beis din and everything, you want
to prove something.
I totally agree with you, which is why at least the conclusion
is okay, but the הוה אמינא hava amina here, you know, first
you're trying to figure out the evidence, but you're right, the the
nobody says like למסקנא lemaskana that that's the problem that you don't
get מלקות. malkos. But I agree, the the possibility that we're contemplating
is bizarre because of everything you would think this is the worst.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says it seems like it's excluding that
case, ולא אכלתי דלא לקי, velo achalti delo laky, that you don't
get lashes by שוא. shav. get lashes, but maybe this case? No.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, no, you're right, it's excluding that
case, but to tell you a different point. זוהי zohi this בשוא
be-shav is the שגגת פרט מקרבן. ashgaas perat mikorban. This is the
one that there's no קרבן korban for if it's done unintentionally. אבל
אכלתי ולא אכלתי, aval achalti velo achalti, but the case of אכלתי
achalti or לא אכלתי, lo achalti, אשגגתה חייב קרבן. ashgaas-ha chayiv korban.
You would bring a קרבן korban ורבי עקיבא היא דמחייב לשעבר כלהבא
ve-Rabbi Akiva hi de-michayev le-she-avar ke-la-haba and it would be רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that says you bring a קרבן korban, for the past
like the future. Now we've got a little bit of a problem
because we said both clauses in the משנה Mishnah excluded the case
of אכלתי ולא אכלתי. achalti velo achalti. The first clause came to
say that in that case you don't bring a קרבן, korban okay,
because it's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. And now we're saying that it's
coming to imply that in that case you do bring a קרבן
korban. because it's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So we can't have both
of them. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אמרת רישא רבי
ישמעאל. amarta reisha Rabbi Yishmael. You just got through saying that the
first case was to rule like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that the
אכלתי achalti case you don't bring a קרבן. korban רישא רבי ישמעאל
וסיפא רבי עקיבא? reisha Rabbi Yishmael ve-seifa Rabbi Akiva? How could that
be
that the whole case that they're referring to, they're taking opposite positions
on whether you do or don't bring a קרבן korban. by the
case of אכלתי? achalti? So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, you got
me. כולה רבי עקיבא. kula Rabbi Akiva. It's all רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that in the past you do bring a
קרבן. korban ורישא לאו למיעוטי אכלתי ולא אכלתי מקרבן. ve-reisha lav le-imutei
achalti velo achalti mikorban. The first case that says when it's future,
that's when you bring a קרבן korban. and get מלקות, malkus, it
doesn't mean that if it's in the past you don't bring a
קרבן. korban אבל למיעוטי אוכל ולא אוכל ממלקות, aval le-imutei ochel velo
ochel mi-malkus, wait, it says, right, if you take a שבועה shvua,
that you won't eat and you do eat, then you get מלקות
malkus or a קרבן korban depending on whether it's intentional. So if
you... no, because then you did an action. You say you won't
eat and you did eat, then you'll get מלקות malkus because you
did an action. So when it says this is the case, it
doesn't mean to contrast it to the past, it means to contrast
it to a similar שבועה shvua... but when you're passive. You say
you will eat and you passively don't eat, then you're not going
to get מלקות malkus because then you're passive.
אבל קרבן מחייב, aval
korban michayev, but a קרבן korban you will bring. ומאי שנא? u-mai
shna? Why should I say that this is talking about the future
and the second case is talking about the past? מסתברא קאי בלהבא
ממעיט להבא, קאי בלהבא ממעיט לשעבר? mistavra kai be-la-haba mema-it la-haba, kai
be-la-haba mema-it le-she-avar? Since we're talking about the future, we're contrasting it
to another future case. We wouldn't be talking about the future and
contrasting it to a past case. Because that was pretty complicated but
that was just to sort of pull back and explain, the משנה
Mishnah here does not talk about the classic case of אכלתי achalti
that when you use a שבועה shvua. to lie, okay, to say
I did something and you're lying or I didn't do something and
you're lying. It says when you say it about the future and
you violate what you said, then you'll bring a קרבן korban or
get מלקות. malkus. When you say a שוא shav like in vain,
then no קרבן korban, but yes מלקות. malkus. What about this middle
case of אכלתי? achalti? So it says okay, so it says that
middle case we're saying yes קרבן, korban, yes מלקות. malkus. So when
it says in vain, in vain yes מלקות, malkus, no קרבן, korban.
the contrast is to a similar type of a thing that is
past-oriented, אכלתי ולא אכלתי. achalti velo achalti, And that's not like one
in vain. In vain, מלקות malkus but no קרבן. korban. אכלתי ולא
velo? אכלתי, מלקות malkus and a קרבן. korban, The one that says
in the future you get מלקות malkus and a קרבן, korban it's
not contrasting it to the past. It's contrasting it to another future
case. If you say in the future you will do something and
you passively don't, that's a case where yes קרבן korban but no
מלקות. malkus. I hope everybody has that clear. There's going to be
a pop quiz tomorrow.
It's quite confusing. But we are now at the conclusion. Let me
just give you the bottom line conclusion. Okay, let's make it simple.
You only bring a קרבן korban in all these cases if you
are unintentional, okay, not if you're willful. Okay, that's point number one.
Now, you only bring a קרבן korban. if you are taking a
שבועה shvua, according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We'll just talk about
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. That if you will do something and you
passively don't do it, or you won't do something and you do
it, or about something you've done or haven't done in the past,
you're lying with it. In those cases, if you are accidentally transgressing,
you bring a קרבן. korban If you are willful and you take
a future שבועה shevuah? about the future or the past, so if
it's about the past, as soon as you say the words, you're
transgressing and you get מלקות. malkus. If it's about the future, you
only transgress when you keep it or don't keep it, and you
only get מלקות malkus when you actively violate. Okay, that's about מלקות.
malkus. And a שבועת שוא you always get מלקות. malkus. So that's
about as simple as I can make it. Okay, but these are...
this is what we will continue to revisit these cases. Yes.
And there's an issue with not using God's name and also ongoing
personality issue of the individual who's taken... Right. Right. And the conceptual
question is: is the
prohibition about the act of the oath that is... That itself is
a violation. That's clearly when it's a שבועת שוא, it's clearly when
it's a שבועת שקר about the past. The act of taking the
vow is itself using God's name either in vain or to lie.
And the interesting conceptual question is, when I take an oath about
the future and I don't keep it, what is my violation? Is
my violation what I do later, that I haven't kept the שבועה,
shevuah or is my violation that by not keeping it in the
future, I've turned what I have said before into a lie? And
in the end, it's about the fact that it wound up that
I lied through my oath. Yes, Bobby.
So, would I be correct in thinking that all these acts of
cleansing and purification are something of course involving the temple? So now,
we're all sinners because there is no temple and we do all
these things potentially unintentionally. And there's no way of atoning. Well, תשובה,
teshuva, יום כיפור... Yom Kippur... But I mean, is there really תשובה
teshuva the way it would then
with the קרבן korban and the...?
Right, so that's what we discussed the other day about sort of
the role of the קרבן korban and so on. For example, by
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the גמרא Gemara basically says that in the
absence of the קרבן korban, and implicitly says that the day of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur serves the same function. רמב״ם Rambam sort of
says in the absence of קרבן, korban תשובה teshuva serves the same
function. But חז״ל Chazal in general understand that full תשובה teshuva is
just as possible now as when there were קרבנות. korbanot. That certain,
and I mean full atonement, that תשובה teshuva and so on serve
those functions, okay? But it gets into a larger question about the
sort of role of קרבנות korbanot and is what we do today
only some type of a substitute for the true ways of atoning,
or are they an equal and parallel track? Because the קרבן korban.
is, presumably, goes throughout the year. When you do something, you respond
to it. Whereas יום כיפור Yom Kippur is one time during the
year and...
Right, there's a famous, so very often we bemoan, as is very
appropriate, תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is coming up, the absence of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because we cannot bring קרבנות. korbanot. But
there's one מדרש, midrash, for example, where somebody is bemoaning the loss
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and I think it is, who
is it that responds? I think it's רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai, who was a very important figure in sort of
in transitioning the Jewish people from a מזבח mizbeach focused Judaism to
after the חורבן churban to like a Torah focused Judaism. And he
doesn't say that, he says, well, let's say תשובה teshuva counts as
a substitute, he doesn't say substitute. He says תשובה teshuva and מעשים
טובים maasim tovim are as effective as a קרבן. korban, They're not
as a substitute for the קרבן, korban. they do just as good
as a קרבן. korban, What about lashes? So, yeah, that he doesn't
say. Right. No, but look, what you are saying is why before
יום כיפור Yom Kippur some communities had a practice of actually administering
pseudo-lashes, because they felt that... Yeah, they felt there was this need
of some more physical act of tangible cleansing. It's why like, one
thing, that's why we do sort of like a תשליך. tashlich. There
is a need of like a ritual that makes you feel you've
done it and you're done. So that is, that type of thing
is definitely lacking. He specifically mentioned שבועות and referring to this kind
of שבועה... shevuah Yeah, any type of שבועה. shevuah But yes, including
this. There you go. Right. And does he ever approach נדרים the
same way as שבועות? Because of this.
Very interesting. Okay. All right. Now we continue. שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל
כל
שהוא.
Shvua shelo ochal
veachal kol shehu.
Now we sort of switch gears and we talk about how much
you have to eat.
So if somebody takes an oath that he
won't eat and he's eaten a tiny bit, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says you transgress even a tiny bit. And חכמים Chachamim say,
since when does anybody transgress by eating a tiny bit? You have
to eat a כזית. kezayit. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says back,
well, since when does anybody transgress and get lashes just by saying
words? Now, what does that mean? So רש״י... Rashi... so תוספות Tosafot
says, well, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying, look, this is such
a weighty transgression that you transgress just with words, that since it's
weighty, we should assume that if you take an oath, you meant
it in a very weighty way. So I won't eat means I
won't even eat a tiny bit. That's what תוספות Tosafot says. What's
my psychological mindset? רש״י Rashi suggests something slightly different and רב סולובייצ׳יק
Rav Soloveitchik is actually interesting, he has a nice write-up of his
שיעורים shiurim on this פרק. perek. And he says that no, that
this is exactly the question of what happens when I take an
oath that I won't eat in the future. Is it like a
נדר? neder When I say a נדר, neder. if I take a
vow, I won't eat this fruit, okay? And I now violate it,
it's not that I lied in my vow. It's that I violated
the status of the fruit. So the transgression is לחיוב גברא, l'chiyuv
hagavra, but the point that some ראשונים rishonim say, let's say I
take a vow, you are forbidden to get benefit from my fruit,
from this fruit. And these fruit are forbidden to you. I take
that vow. And you go ahead and eat it. So according to
some ראשונים, rishonim, you violate. I was the one who made the
vow, but I gave the fruit a status and you've sort of
violated the status, you violate. So it's not about the vow, it's
about the status. So when I say I won't eat this loaf
of bread, but you do it in a שבועה, shevuah, which normally
relates to the person, what is the transgression? Is the transgression that
I have, you know, that I will violate my word? in the
future, or is the transgression that retroactively I said something false? It
was שקר. Okay? Or was it the violation of the status and
the obligation and
so on? So Rav Soloveitchik says that's the question about whether you
need a כזית. kezayit. Because a כזית kezayit is the amount that
normally is the what when it's forbidden food, is a כזית. kezayit.
So if you say it changes the status, creates this obligation, it's
like any other obligation and not to eat something, it's defined as
an you violate that when you eat a כזית. kezayit. But if
the point is that I've made my words false, then as soon
as I've eaten a tiny bit, even less than a כזית, kezayit,
it might not be considered an act of eating to violate qua
an act of eating, but what I have done is now my
words have been falsified. Okay? And a lie is a lie, a
little lie or a big lie. Right. Exactly. Okay. So that's why
Rabbi Akiva says, but this is the prohibition that you transgress with
words, meaning it's not a prohibition of eating per se, it's a
prohibition of violating your words, so even the smallest amount violates your
words. Okay, so now we're going to look at that debate. איבעיא
להו. ibaia lehu. So they ask the question: Rabbi Akiva, בכל התורה
כולה be-chol ha-Torah kulah כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה? ke-Rabbi Shimon sevira leh?
Does he hold in the entire other areas of the Torah like
Rabbi Shimon? Rabbi Shimon says for all prohibited eatings, you transgress when
you eat a tiny bit. So maybe he holds like Rabbi Shimon
דמחייב במשהו de-mechayev be-mashehu that obligates even in the tiniest amount. דתניא,
de-tanya, Rabbi Shimon says, כל שהוא למלקות, kol she-hu le-malkot, you eat
a tiny bit of חלב chelev or of בשר בחלב, basar be-chalav,
a tiny bit of forbidden food, you get lashes. לא אמרו כזית,
lo amru kezayit, when they said you need a כזית, kezayit, an
olive size, they only say it אלא לעניין קרבן, ela le-inyan korban,
only to bring a קרבן, korban, that if it was done unintentionally,
but willful is like more of a violation and even the tiniest
bit you get lashes. Okay. ובדין הוא, u-vedin hu, so if he
holds like Rabbi Shimon, ובדין הוא, u-vedin hu, really in truth, דבפלוגתא
בעלמא, de-viflugeta be-alma, he could have said to the rabbis in all
prohibited eatings even the tiniest bit you get lashes. That's like a
בריה, biryah, right, בריה שלמה? biryah sheleimah? What? You know, it's like
a בריה. biryah. Yeah, we'll get to that. והאי דקמפלגי הכא, ve-hai
de-kamiflegi hacha, so why does he only debate this case of a
שבועה? shevuah להודיעך כוחן דרבנן, le-hodiacha kochan de-Rabbanan, to tell you how
far the rabbis go who disagree. דאף על גב דאיכא למימר de-af
al gav de-ika le-meimar הואיל ומפרש חייב, ho-il u-mefaresh chayav, סתם נמי
חייב. stam nami chayav. Because you could say by שבועה shevuah we
know there are cases where you transgress with a tiny bit. What's
the cases where you transgress with a tiny bit? If you say
explicitly I won't eat even a tiny bit. So since there are
cases of שבועה shevuah. where you do transgress, I could have said
that even if you don't say a tiny bit, nevertheless you transgress
with a tiny bit, that שבועה shvua doesn't fit the normal categories
of always needing a כזית. kezayit. So קמשמע לן דפטורי, ka mashma
lan de-patori, that even there they exempt. So one way is that
Rabbi Akiva maybe in general holds a tiny bit, but he's—but so
there's nothing unique about a שבועה, shvua but the rabbis go so
far to say not only do you need a כזית kezayit in
other cases, you even need it here. או דלמא, o dilma, or
should we say the more logical point, דבעלמא כרבנן סבירא ליה, de-ve-alma
ke-Rabbanan sevira leh, in general he holds you need a כזית kezayit
by forbidden foods. והכא היינו טעמא, ve-hacha hainu ta-ama, so why here
does he argue and say even a tiny bit? הואיל ומפרש חייב,
ho-il u-mefaresh chayav, סתם נמי חייב. stam nami chayav. Since it's possible
to transgress with a tiny bit if you say explicitly I won't
eat a tiny bit, so even if you don't say explicitly that,
a שבועה shvua is different. A שבועה shvua does not necessarily need
a כזית. kezayit. And again, the way the Rav explained it, which
was it doesn't need a כזית kezayit because it's not about the
eating per se, it's about the violating of the שבועה. shvua, Now,
that actually relates to another question which I'm waiting for somebody to
ask, which is: here חייב chayav means bringing a קרבן, korban. right?
So how could we say that Rabbi Shimon is relevant to this?
Rabbi Shimon says a tiny bit for lashes, but a כזית kezayit
for קרבן. korban. So how could we say, oh maybe this is
based on the position of Rabbi Shimon? Here we are talking about
a קרבן. korban? Everyone understand the question? Right, here the question: do
you bring a קרבן? korban. So Rabbi Shimon's position of a tiny
bit for lashes isn't relevant, because he says you need a כזית
kezayit for a קרבן. korban So Tosafot says it depends what the
קרבן korban is in exchange for. If the קרבן korban normally is
in exchange for כרת, karet, right, so for כרת, karet, which if
you be intentional, for that you need a כזית, kezayit, so for
the קרבן korban you need a כזית. kezayit. Here, by a false
oath, you don't get כרת. karet. What's the worst you can get
if you're intentional by a false oath? מלקות. malkot. So since the
קרבן korban is in exchange for מלקות, malkot, and the מלקות malkot
is a משהו, mashehu, the קרבן korban is also a משהו. mashehu.
So that's how Tosafot explains why it's relevant. Rashi, however, very consistently
says no, here's why it's not an issue. When I eat a—when
I bring a קרבן korban and I need a כזית kezayit for
a קרבן korban according to Rabbi Shimon, that's because my קרבן korban
is for the amount that I've eaten. So I only when I
do a significant amount. Here, what's my קרבן korban? for? Is it
for the amount I've eaten? Is that what it's for, or for
what sin is my קרבן? korban, Not really for eating, but for
lying, for violating my words. That I—that's done as soon as I
get the first little bit. Okay, or you just forgot, so that
advances the question as to why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is relevant.
Because when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says a כל שהוא kol shehu
is enough to transgress, רש״י Rashi says when he says you need
a certain amount for a קרבן, korban it's when the קרבן korban.
relates to, it's about the eating per se being the sin. So
he needs a כזית kezayis for קרבן. korban Here you've done the
שיעור, shiur, you've totally violated your word. There's saying you need a
more or less violation for כזית kezayis for קרבן korban in both
cases, and not this case? Here you need a קרבן korban even
in a כל שהוא? kol shehu? Right, correct, yeah. Okay, so now
we go on. So does רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, is he specifically
tied into רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and in general even a tiny
bit, or specifically here? So let's take a look. תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear. דאמרו ליה לרבי עקיבא, De'amru leh leRabbi Akiva,
the rabbis said back to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, היכן מצינו באוכל
כל שהוא חייב שזה חייב? Heichan matzinu be'ocheil kol shehu chayav she'zeh
chayav? The rabbis said when have we ever found that a tiny
bit is an obligation, is transgressing? אם איתא, Im issa, if רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds that that's generally true, לימא להו, leima lehu,
let him say back to them: אנא בכל התורה כולה כרבי שמעון
סבירא לי! Ana bechol haTorah kullah keRabbi Shimon sevira li! Yeah, I
hold that you always get lashes and transgress when you eat a
little bit. So this is an easy answer. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, דדברי דרבנן קאמר להו. de'divrei de'rabbanan ka'amar lehu. He's answering
back according to their position. לדידי, Ledidi, for myself, בכל התורה כולה
כרבי שמעון סבירא לי. bechol haTorah kullah keRabbi Shimon sevira li. I
generally hold like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and therefore that your question
is a non-question because yeah, I usually hold a tiny bit is
a problem. But לדידכו, ledidchu, but even according to you that you
say normally a tiny bit is not a problem, אודי לי מיהא
הואיל ומפרש חייב סתם נמי חייב. odi li miha hu'il u'mefaresh chayav
stam nami chayav. You should admit to me that here a little
bit is a problem, because since you can, it's possible to violate
with a little bit if you explicitly say a little bit, so
therefore it's also possible to violate even if you don't explicitly say
it. ואמרו ליה רבנן, Ve'amru leh rabbanan, and the rabbis say: No,
no, we're not convinced! If you say it explicitly then you transgress,
but if you don't say it explicitly, you need a כזית. kezayis.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, you gotta love that bit with the
voice. No, okay, that's not... תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear:
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, נזיר ששרה פיתו ביין, nazir shesharah
pito be'yayin, ששר shashar excuse me, a נזיר nazir who dips his
bread in wine and eats a כזית, kezayis, but the כזית kezayis
is not all wine, it's half wine and half bread. Okay, ויש
בה כדי לצרף כזית חייב, ve'yesh bah kedei letzaref kezayis chayav, as
long as the combination of wine and bread is a כזית, kezayis,
you are חייב. chayav. Now, and that's a special דין din by
נזיר. nazir. Normally you would have to eat a כזית kezayis of
the forbidden thing itself, but by נזיר nazir we combine היתר מצטרף
לאיסור. heter mitztaref le'issur. Yeah, but if it's דרך אכילה, derech achila,
it's a כזית kezayis and I don't want to discuss it. Okay,
so ואי סלקא דעתך, ve'issa salka da'atach, but what do you see?
You see that he needs to get you to a כזית. kezayis.
So clearly for him a tiny bit is not enough. ואי סלקא
דעתך בעלמא כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה, ve'issa salka da'atach be'alma keRabbi Shimon
sevira leh, if he would generally hold like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
למה לי לצרף, lama li letzaref, why do you have to combine
to get to a כזית, kezayis, because even a tiny bit is
already a transgression? ותנן, Ve'utnan, and we taught another משנה mishna later
on: שבועה שלא אוכל, Shvua shelo ochal, if a person takes an
שבועה shvua not to eat, ואכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים, ve'achal neveilos
u'tereifos shkatzim u'remasim, and you ate all these disgusting foods which are
all already forbidden. Okay, so does the שבועה shvua. take effect? Because
normally we have a principle of אין איסור חל על איסור. ein
issur chal al issur. If it's already forbidden, a שבועה shvua cannot
make it forbidden on top of being
already forbidden, like before when you took a שבועה shvua on top
of a שבועה, shvua the second one was not meaningful.
But the משנה mishna says חייב, chayav, that you are חייב. chayav.
רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts because
it's איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. והוינן בה, Ve'havinan
bah, and we discussed it, אמאי חייב, amai chayav, how could you
be חייב? chayav? מושבע מהר סיני הוא, Mushba me'Har Sinai hu, you
are already forsworn at הר סיני Har Sinai not to do it,
so another שבועה shvua does not take effect on top of this
שבועה. shvua So the גמרא Gemara says: רב ושמואל ורבי יוחנן דאמרי,
Rav ve'Shmuel ve'Rabbi Yochanan de'amri, now they take out the word תרוייהו
tavayhu because it was three people, דאמרי de'amri who say: בכולל דברים
המותרים עם דברים האסורים. becol devarim hamutarim im devarim ha'asurim. Since you
say I won't eat anything today, so you're not limiting yourself with
just forbidden food, and since your שבועה shvua. takes effect on permissible
food, it also takes effect on the forbidden food. Okay, so if
it's not directly, if it's a broader scope because for the other
stuff, the permissible food it has effect, it has effect even on
the forbidden. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees, he would not hold
of that principle. He would say it never takes effect on what
was already forbidden. That's answer number one, בכולל דברים המותרים עם דברים
האסורים. becol devarim hamutarim im devarim ha'asurim. ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish
amar, but ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says a different approach: אי אתה
מוצא, I attah motzei, you don't have this case, אלא אי במפרש
חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן, ella i bimefaresh chatzi shiur ve'aliba de'rabbanan, either
you say I won't eat even a half a כזית, kezayis, so
then it does take effect, because then you're making something newly forbidden.
This נבילה nevela was not forbidden before until you ate a כזית...
kezayis... No, but you're just not punished until you eat a כזית.
kezayis. Okay, I'm gonna talk about that in a minute. But here
and now you've made it forbidden even by a half a כזית.
kezayis. So then your new שבועה shvua has had effect. That's according
to the rabbis that you say explicitly half a כזית. kezayis. ואי
בסתם Ve'i bistem Or even if you just סתם stam said a
שבועה shvua אליבא דרבי עקיבא, aliba d'Rabbi Akiva, because since Rabbi Akiva
says that a שבועה shvua forbids you even eating a tiny bit,
the שבועה shvua has effect beyond the biblical prohibition. The biblical prohibition
is only for a כזית, kezayis, and this is even for a
tiny bit. דאמר אדם אוסר עצמו בכל שהוא, d'amar adam oser atzmo
be-khol shehu, that even a כל שהוא. kol shehu. And now we're
going to prove our point that Rabbi Akiva says this uniquely by
שבועה. shvua דאי סלקא דעתך בעלמא כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה, de-isa daitaich
b'alma k'Rabbi Shimon sevira lei, if Rabbi Akiva in general held like
Rabbi Shimon that all forbidden foods are a כל שהוא, kol shehu,
כל שהוא נמי מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא. kol shehu nami mushba
ve-omed me-Har Sinai hu. So even the tiniest bit for נבלה neveila
and שקצים shkatzim and all these forbidden foods is also forbidden. So
your שבועה shvua. doesn't add anything new. So then you can't be
חייב. chayiv. So you see that according to ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish
interpretation, he clearly is arguing only here. אלא לאו שמע מינה בעלמא
כרבנן סבירא ליה, ella lav shema mina b'alma k'rabbanan sevira lei, you
see in general you would have to eat a כזית, kezayis, שבועה
shvua. is unique, שמע מינה shema mina you've made that good proof.
Now we've said that normally you need a כזית, kezayis, here שבועה
shvuah. is unique. We haven't said exactly why, we've alluded to the
fact because we said, well since you can make it explicit even
if you said it סתם. stam. So you could explicitly say even
a little bit. So some like תוספות ריד Tosafot Rid that again,
that therefore since such a שבועה is possible, and since obviously שבועות
are strict, presumably we're going to assume that that was your intention
to define it in the strictest way. But again I gave you
the explanation that Rav Soloveitchik gives, which fits with some רש"י, Rashis,
which says that no, the point is that here it's about violating
your word, and not about the act of eating per se. The
act of eating needs כזית, kezayis, if you violate your word as
soon as you've done a little bit. Now Michael raises a good
question, which is, here it says that it's not a problem if
you do less than a שיעור, shiur, so your שבועה can take
effect. But Michael says one minute, we have a whole discussion in
יומא, Yoma, the eighth פרק, perek, that חצי שיעור chatzi shiur is
forbidden according to Rabbi Yochanan is biblically forbidden. So it is already
biblically forbidden. So it seems like the answer is, תוספות Tosafot asks
that question, and תוספות Tosafot says it might be biblically forbidden, but
it's not, you know, it's not like you get lashes for it,
it's not like it's an explicit איסור. issur. So if a lighter
prohibition and something which is explicitly אסור assur and something that you
get lashes for, that will take effect on the biblical prohibition of
a חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur, which is more like a type of
amorphous generic prohibition. Okay, there's more to say about that but that's
what I'll say for now. Okay, so here you have the debate
about whether you get it even in less than a כזית. kezayis.
Rabbi Akiva says yes, again that might point towards the question about
the nature of a חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur, but also to the
nature of why you violate for שבועה. And now a future-oriented שבועה.
Now we are going to look at some other cases. So let's
take a look. Delo, I'm sorry, אמר לו לרבי עקיבא היכן מצינו,
amar lo le-Rabbi Akiva heichan matzinu, we've never found before that you
violate for less than a כזית. kezayis. So the Gemara says ולא?
Have we not? והרי, ve-harei, behold, נמלה, nemala, an ant. Okay, if
you eat a whole ant, so it's less than a כזית. kezayis.
What about an uncle? Right. So the Gemara says בריה שאני. berya
shani. No, if it's a whole unit, that's different, then that's of
significance in itself. Okay, but something that is just stuff, amount of
meat, so there's nothing qualitatively that makes it significant, there you need
a quantitative amount, a כזית kezayis to give it significance. Okay, but
something that's a unit in itself, that has qualitative significance. That's בריה.
berya. והרי הקדש. ve-harei hekdesh. So how about if you eat הקדש
hekdesh and you do the sin of מעילה? me'ila? You can violate
even less than a כזית. kezayis. So the Gemara says הא בעינן
שוה פרוטה. ha ba'inan shaveh prutah. No, that has nothing to do
with the act of eating per se, that's you violated because you
have stolen from הקדש. hekdesh. And there is a שיעור, shiur, it's
just a different שיעור, shiur, it's a שיעור shiur for stealing. So
a שיעור shiur for eating is a כזית, kezayis, a שיעור shiur
for stealing is a פרוטה's prutah worth, a penny's worth. So that
has nothing to do with it, it's not about eating, it's about
stealing. So your eating is an act of stealing. והרי מפרש. ve-harei
mefaresh. How about if you make your oath and you explicitly say
I won't eat even a tiny bit? So the Gemara says מפרש
נמי כבריה דמי. mefaresh nami ke-berya dami. That's also different, then you
have specifically identified the tiny bit as being significant, meaning the way
I explain the comparison is, as I said before, if you've just
have stuff, a little bit isn't significant, you need a quantitative amount.
But you can have something that's qualitatively significant, a בריה, berya, it's
a unit in itself, or you give significance to a little bit
by saying I won't eat a little bit. But if you haven't
given particular significance and it's not qualitatively significant, then you need a
certain quantity to be considered transgressing and violating. Okay, והרי עפר. ve-harei
afar. How about if you take an oath not to eat dirt?
So we're going to see later that because normal people don't eat
dirt, it's not defined as a normal act of eating, right, and
therefore it's defined even by a little bit you transgress. So wouldn't
that be an example? So the Gemara says אלא תפשוט דבי רבא,
ella tipshot d'bei Rava, let's use the fact that they are not
into this case to to conclude the question of רבא Rava *Rava*
that רבא *Rava* asked: שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל עפר בכמה *Shvu'a she-lo
okhal ve-akhal afar be-kama*. If he says an oath that I won't
eat and he eats dirt, okay, how much? Now he might have
to say an oath that I won't eat dirt because a normal
oath that I won't eat might only refer to edible things. But
how much dirt do you need to eat if that's your oath?
So תפשוט דעדי איכא כזית kezayis. *tipshot de-adei ika kezayit*, let's conclude
that you need a כזית *kezayit* because if not, that would be
the evidence, you know, when they said to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*,
you never have a case of a little bit, why didn't he
give this example? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, for obvious
reasons. כי אמרינן *Ki amrina* when do the rabbis say you need
a כזית *kezayit*? במידי דבר אכילה *B'midi de-var akhila*. Something that is
normally eaten, that eating is only defined by a כזית *kezayit*, קאמרינן
*kamrinan*. So therefore, if the whole logic of רבא *Rava* is that
dirt doesn't need a כזית *kezayit*, it's because dirt is not normally
eaten. So the rabbis' argument to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is when
have we ever found something that's normally eaten that you get by
with less than a כזית *kezayit*? The גמרא *Gemara* says well how
about the following: והרי קונמות Konamos *Ve-harei konamoth*? א קונמות *konamoth* is
another word for a נדר *neder*. If I say this food is
אסור *assur* to me, the standard language of a שבועה *shvu'a*, שבועה
*shvu'a*. שבועה *Shvu'a* I'll do this, שבועה *shvu'a* I won't do that
and refers to what you're going to do. The standard language of
a נדר *neder* refers to the object, and often like one of
the classic technical words is קונם konam *konam*, which is really like
a paraphrase of the word קרבן korban? *korban*, okay, because by a
נדר *neder* it's like you give a status to an object like
a קרבן korban. *korban*. So a word that people would use rather
than saying קרבן korban, *korban* is קונם konam, *konam*. So you would
say קונם konam *konam* this fruit. This fruit is קונם *konam*. This
fruit is אסור *assur* to me קונם *konam*. So that's קונמות *konamoth*.
It's נדר *neder* when it relates to the object. So the גמרא
*Gemara* takes for granted here that you violate that even with a
כל שהוא kol shehu *kol she-hu*, so that really is parallel to
a שבועה *shvu'a*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, קונמות נמי כמפרש דמי
k'mefaresh dami. *Konamoth nami ki-mefaresh dami*. So קונמות *konamoth* is like you
made it explicit. Now why? Why is it like you made it
explicit more than a שבועה *shvu'a*? So what רש"י *Rashi* says is
that by a שבועה *shvu'a* you say, שבועה *shvu'a* I won't eat.
You specifically relate to the act of eating. So your transgression is
defined by eating. So eating is defined as a כזית *kezayit*. But
when you say this is a קונם *konam*, you don't say any
words about eating. You just say like this is like sanctified, forbidden,
you don't say the word eating. So the transgression does not so
much focus on the act of eating as defined as a, you
know, focusing on that as an act. It's defined as violating the
status. And therefore you don't need a, you don't need a כזית
*kezayit* even a כל שהוא *kol she-hu*. We are going to see
later that there's even the opinions that you transgress מעילה meilah, *me'ila*,
the prohibition for misusing הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* when you make something אסור
בנדר *assur b'neder*. So it really has this very similar comparison to
הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* and it's not for eating per se but it's
for violating the status and even a כל שהוא *kol she-hu*. Yeah,
then you just said that if you take the other view that
it's about reneging on your word then it is a כל שהוא
*kol she-hu*. But this is the חכמים *Chachamim* that say that a
שבועה *shvu'a* is a כזית *kezayit* but they're willing to admit that
a קונם *konam* is different, okay, and a קונם *konam* is a
כל שהוא *kol she-hu*. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says we'll
see more about קונמות *konamoth* later. Let's try to get a little
bit further. אמר להן *Amar lahen*, so he said back to them:
This is special, היכא מצינו במדבר מביא קרבן שזה מדבר ומביא קרבן
*Heikha matzin b'midaber mevi korban she-zeh midaber mevi korban*? This is special,
this you bring a קרבן *korban* even for speech. Okay, now again,
two ways to explain that. תוספות *Tosafot* says that shows it's weighty
so you mean a כל שהוא *kol she-hu*. And again, רש"י *Rashi*
or whatever the way רב סולובייצ'יק *Rav Soloveitchik* interprets רש"י *Rashi* says,
since it's about violating the speech act, you don't focus on the
act of eating. Any כל שהוא *kol she-hu* means you violated what
you said. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* now is just going to
question is this really true that you don't bring קרבנות *korbanos* for
speech acts? So lo, is that is that do you not? והרי
מגדף *Ve-harei megadef*, somebody who curses God. So therefore and that you
bring a קרבן *korban*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, מדבר ואוסר קאמרינן
*midaber ve-oser kamrinan*. What רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says is when the
speech act creates a prohibition. דהאי מדבר וחוטא הוא *De-hai midaber ve-khotei
hu*. Here, as soon as he speaks he's violating. But we're talking
about speaking and then creating a prohibition which is violated later. והרי
נזיר מביא *Ve-harei nazir mevi*. So the נזיר *nazir* you did a
speech act and then you bring a קרבן *korban* at the end
of your נזירות *nezirut*. So that's different. מביא קרבנו על דיבורו קאמרינן
*Mevi korbano al diburo kamrinan*. We're talking about when the קרבן *korban*
is because you something happened wrong with your speech. Your speech was
violated. האי *Hai*, this נזיר *nazir* מביא קרבנו לשרויי לחמרא הוא דקאתי
*mevi korbano le-sharuyei le-khamra hu de-ka-ati*. He's bringing a קרבן *korban* not
because he violated his speech, he's bringing a קרבן *korban* because his
נזירות *nezirut* is over and it is the way of ending his
נזירות *nezirut*. It's a process to end his נזירות *nezirut*, not for
having violated his speech. והרי הקדש hekdesh. *Ve-harei hekdesh*? How about if
you sanctify an object and then you misuse it, right, and you
do מעילה meilah *me'ila*? So you have violated your speech act and
you bring a קרבן *korban*. That actually is very analogous. You say
words that create obligations, you violate them, then you bring a קרבן
*korban*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: אוסר לעצמו קאמרינן *Oser le-atzmo kamrinan*.
We keep on narrowing it so that this is the only case.
Once you define it exactly like this case, then it's the only
case. Yeah, I don't have an answer. Okay. אוסר לעצמו קאמרינן והאי
אוסר כל העולם כולו הוא. That where we're talking about when your
speech act makes something forbidden just to you. A הקדש hekdesh? you've
given it a status for the whole world when you sanctify an
object. So the גמרא says okay, but הרי קונמות, harei konamos, a
נדר, I can say this fruit is to me קונם or is
to you קונם, not to the whole world but just to me
or just to you. And if I violate it, so now the
question is do you bring a קרבן for violating a נדר? For
נדר you get מלקות, malkus, do you bring a קרבן? So the
answer is only if you consider a נדר to be like הקדש
hekdesh, and to be have and therefore you would have transgressed מעילה,
Meilah misuse of הקדש. hekdesh, For מעילה meilah. you bring a קרבן.
So do you go that far to think of that a נדר
is like הקדש? hekdesh, So not necessarily. So the גמרא's going to
say קסבר אין מעילה בקונמות. kasvar ein meilah b'konamos. מעילה meilah, is
not like הקדש, there is no מעילה. קונמות is not like הקדש,
there is no מעילה, it's not considered misuse of הקדש, so there
is no קרבן, there is just מלקות malkus for violating a נדר.
So if we've defined it narrowly enough, there's no other case like
it. All right. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא said מחלוקת בסתם.
machlokes b'stam. This debate is only if you just said "I won't
eat." אבל במפרש, Aval b'mefaresh, now this is just really clarifying what
we said before, if you explicitly said "I won't eat a tiny
bit," דברי הכל בכל שהוא, divrei hakol b'chol shehu, then okay, then
that works because you said explicitly. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why? מפרש
נמי כבריה דמי. mefaresh nami k'biryah dami. That's like a בריה, biryah,
it's a bizarre comparison. It's clear why you bring a why if
you explain explicitly because you violated explicitly what you said. Okay, but
again if you think that the focus for the רבנן rabbanan is
not on your speech act but about the act that you do
later that is now forbidden, right, so you can't it's not enough
to say you violate what you have to say what you said
gave significance to the act you're doing now. So the same way
a בריה, biryah, a whole ant gives significance, qualitative significance, your act
of defining a כל שהוא gave significance to that act that you're
doing now. Let's just read one more one more line, get a
little further. ואמר רבא V'amar Rava מחלוקת בשלא אוכל. machlokes b'shelo ochel.
If you say "I won't eat," that that might be a כזית.
אבל בשלא אטעום Aval b'shelo et'om say "I won't taste," דברי הכל
בכל שהוא הוא. divrei hakol b'chol shehu hu. That's a tiny bit,
tasting is a little bit. פשיטא Pshita obviously. No. מהו דתימא ליטעם
נמי כדאמרי אינשי Mah d'teima lito'am nami k'de'amri inshi even when you
say taste, it's like people say, like say קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan not. Like people say "Oh, let me just I'm just
going to have a little taste" and then you know they really
eat. So no, taste means taste. Okay.
Maybe okay well I again I'll just read רב פפא again because
it fleshes out what we just said. אמר רב פפא מחלוקת בשבועות.
Amar Rav Pappa machlokes b'shvuos. The debate is by a שבועה. אבל
בקונמות Aval b'konamos is all really just you know elaborating on what
we said before. If you said קונם and then you ate it,
so and you made the food forbidden not yourself, דברי הכל בכל
שהוא. divrei hakol b'chol shehu. That's even a small amount. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? Why? קונמות נמי כיון דלא מדכר
שמא דאכילה Konamos nami keivan d'lo madkar shema d'achilah since you don't
use the word "eating" you just focus on the status not on
the act of eating, כמפרש
דמי. So even a small amount is a violation because you don't
focus on the act of eating just on the status of the
object. Okay.